<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../Drools_Guvnor.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter>
         
   <title>Database configuration</title>

   <para>
   Guvnor uses the JCR standard for storing assets such as rules. The default implementation is Apache
   Jackrabbit, <ulink url="http://jackrabbit.apache.org" />. This includes an out of the box storage
   engine/database, which you can use as is, or configure to use an existing RDBMS if needed.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Changing the location of the data store</title>

      <para>
      Assuming you are using on of the JBoss platforms, running Guvnor for the first time will create a
      database in the <filename>bin/</filename> directory of the application server. There will be a
      <filename>repository.xml</filename> file, and a <filename>repository</filename> directory that are
      automatically created.
      </para>

      <para>
      The location of the data store should be a secure location, that is backed up. The default location may
      not be suitable for this, so the easiest way is to set a more suitable location. If you want to change
      this, please make sure you have stopped Guvnor (i.e. stopped the app server or un-deployed the
      application).
      </para>

      <para>
      To change the location, unzip the WAR file, and locate the <filename>components.xml</filename> file in
      the <filename>WEB-INF</filename> directory. This is a JBoss Seam configuration file (Seam is the
      framework used) which allows various parts of the system to be customized. When you have located the
      <filename>components.xml</filename> file, you should see something like the following:
      </para>

      <programlisting language="XML"><![CDATA[<component name="repositoryConfiguration">
   <!--
   *** This is for configuring the "home" directory for the repository storage. the directory must exist. ***
   <property name="homeDirectory">/home/michael/RulesRepository_001</property>
   -->  
   ...
</component>]]></programlisting>

      <para>Find the component with a name of <literal>repositoryConfiguration</literal> and
      the property with the name of <literal>homeDirectory</literal>.</para>

      <para>If you un-comment this (as in the example above it is commented
      out), you can set whatever path you need for the repository data to be
      stored in. You can also use this to move the repository around. In that
      case, when you have set the location in the <filename>components.xml</filename> you can
      simply move the <filename>repository.xml</filename> AND the repository directory to the new
      location that you set in the <filename>components.xml</filename>.</para>

      <para>If there is no repository at the location specified (or in the
      default location) then Guvnor will create a new empty one.</para>

      <para>There are many more options which can be configured in the
      <filename>repository.xml</filename>, but for the most part, it is not recommended to change
      the defaults.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring Guvnor to use an external RDBMS</title>

      <para>In some cases it may be a requirement that you use an external
      RDBMS, such as Oracle, MySQL, or Microsoft SQL Server as the data store
      - this is permitted. In this case, the easiest thing to do is to start
      up Guvnor with defaults (or with a suitable home directory as specified
      above) to let it generate the default <filename>repository.xml</filename> scaffolding.</para>

      <para>Locate the <filename>repository.xml</filename> file that was generated, and open it -
      it will be annotated with comments describing many of the different
      options. From here on, you will need to know a little about Jackrabbit
      Persistence managers, <ulink url="http://wiki.apache.org/jackrabbit/PersistenceManagerFAQ" />.
      </para>

      <para>There are a few persistence managers, some are database specific
      (eg Oracle). There is a SimpleDBPersistenceManager which works with any
      database that supports JDBC - you also specify the database type, so it
      uses the specific DDL to create the table structure (all major databases
      are supported).</para>

      <para>Guvnor will create the tables the first time it is started up if
      it is running against a fresh (empty) RDBMS - so its important to note
      that the user credentials supplied have permissions to create tables (at
      least initially, on first run, after that they could be locked
      down).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Searching and indexing, Version storage</title>

      <para>Jackrabbit has a separate storage area for version storage (as
      over time, the number of old versions will increase, yet it should not
      slow down the performance of the main data store). The version storage
      also has its own persistence manage configuration in the <filename>repository.xml</filename>,
      but for most purposes you can use the same database as the main storage
      (just with a different schema object prefix - ie in your database, all
      the version data will be prefixed with <literal>version_</literal> but otherwise in the
      same tablespace). See the <filename>repository.xml</filename> for more details of
      this.</para>

      <para>Lucene is used to provide indexing across the semi structured
      data, and across versions. This indexing is generally best stored on a
      filesystem, local to Guvnor (as per the default in the <filename>repository.xml</filename>) -
      in most cases the default is fine.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>