<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Guided decision tables (web based)</title>

  <para>The guided decision table feature allows decision tables to be edited
  in place on the web. This works similar to the guided editor by
  introspecting what facts and fields are available to guide the creation of a
  decision table. Rule attributes, meta-data, conditions and actions can be
  defined in a tabular format thus facilitating rapid entry of large sets of
  related rules. Web-based decision table rules are compiled into DRL like all
  other rule assets.</para>

  <para>Cells can be selected in a variety of ways:-<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Firstly individual cells can be double-clicked and a pop-up
        editor corresponding to the underlying data-type will appear. Groups
        of cells in the same column can be selected by either clicking in the
        first and dragging the mouse pointer or clicking in the first and
        clicking the extent of the required range with the shift key
        pressed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Secondly the keyboard cursor keys can be used to navigate around
        the table. Pressing the enter key will pop-up the correspondig editor.
        Ranges can be selected by pressing the shift key whilst extending the
        range with the cursor keys.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <para>Columns can be resized by hovering over the corresponding divider in
  the table header. The mouse cursor will change and then the column width
  dragged either narrower or wider.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Decision table</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/dtable-complete.png"
                   format="PNG" scalefit="1" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <section>
    <title>Main components</title>

    <para>The guided decision table is split into two main
    sections:-<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The upper section allows table columns to be defined
          representing rule attributes, meta-data, conditions and
          actions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The lower section contains the actual table itself; where
          individual rows define seperate rules.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <figure>
      <title>Main components</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/dtable-sections.png"
                     format="PNG" scalefit="1" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Column configuration</title>

    <para>When you edit or create a new column, you will be given a choice of
    the type of constraint:-<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Literal : The value in the cell will be compared with the
          field using the operator.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Formula: The expression in the cell will be evaluated and then
          compared with the field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Predicate : No field is needed, the expression will be
          evaluated to true or false.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>You can set a default value, but normally if there is no value in
    the cell, that constraint will not apply.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Column configuration</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/dtable-column-config.png"
                     format="PNG" scalefit="1" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section>
      <title>Utility columns</title>

      <para>Two columns containing rule number and description are provided by
      default.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Attribute columns</title>

      <para>Zero or more attribue columns representing any of the DRL rule
      attributes can be added. An additional pseudo attribute is provide in
      the guided decision table editor to "negate" a rule. Use of this
      attribute allows complete rules to be negated. For example the following
      simple rule can be negated as also shown.<programlisting>when
  $c : Cheese( name == "Cheddar" )
then
  ...
end</programlisting><programlisting>when
  not Cheese( name == "Cheddar" )
then
  ...
end</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Meta-data columns</title>

      <para>Zero or more meta-data columns can be defined, each represents the
      normal meta-data annotation on DRL rules.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Condition columns</title>

      <para>Conditions represent fact patterns defined in the right-hand side,
      or "when" portion, of a rule. To define a condition column you must
      define a binding to a model class or select one that has previously been
      defined. You can choose to negate the pattern. Once this has been
      completed you can define field constraints. If two or more columns are
      defined using the same fact pattern binding the field constraints become
      composite field constraints on the same pattern. If you define multiple
      bindings for a single model class each binding becomes a seperate model
      class in the right-hand side of the rule.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Action columns</title>

      <para>Action columns can be defined to perform simple operations on
      bound facts within the rule engine's working memory or create new facts
      entirely. New facts can be inserted logically into the rule engine's
      working memory thus being subject to truth maintenance as usual. Please
      refer to the "Drools Expert" documentation for discussion on truth
      maintenance and logical insertions.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Rule definition</title>

    <para>This section alows individual rules to be defined using the columns
    defined earlier.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Rule definition</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/dtable-body.png"
                     format="PNG" scalefit="1" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Cell merging</title>

    <para>The icon in the top left of the decision table toggles cell merging
    on and off. When cells are merged those in the same column with identical
    values are merged into a single cell. This simplifies changing the value
    of multiple cells that shared the same original value. When cells are
    merged they also gain an icon in the top-left of the cell that allows rows
    spanning the merged cell to be grouped.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Cell merging</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/dtable-merged.png"
                     format="PNG" scalefit="1" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Cell grouping</title>

    <para>Cells that have been merged can be further collapsed into a single
    row. Clicking the [+\-] icon in the top left of a merged cell collapses
    the corresponding rows into a single entry. Cells in other columns
    spanning the collapsed rows that have identical values are shown
    unchanged. Cells in other columns spanning the collapsed rows that have
    different values are highlighted and the first value displayed.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Cell grouping</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/dtable-grouped.png"
                     format="PNG" scalefit="1" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>When the value of a grouped cell is altered all cells that have been
    collapsed also have their values updated.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Operation of "otherwise"</title>

    <para>Condition columns defined with literal values that use either the
    equality (==) or inequality (!=) operators can take advantage of a special
    decision table cell value of "otherwise". This special value allows a rule
    to be defined that matches on all values not explicitly defined in all
    other rules defined in the table. This is best illustrated with an
    example:-<programlisting>when
  Cheese( name not in ("Cheddar", "Edam", "Brie") )
  ...
then
  ...
end</programlisting><programlisting>when
  Cheese( name in ("Cheddar", "Edam", "Brie") )
  ...
then
  ...
end</programlisting></para>
  </section>
</section>
