<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
  xml:base="./" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>Installation for most people is very simple. The Guvnor application
    is deployed as a .war file, which can be deployed in application servers
    or servlet containers with little or no configuration if you are happy
    with the defaults.</para>

    <para>When you have downloaded the Guvnor distribution (which you can get
    from http://www.jboss.org/drools), you need to rename drools-5.1.0-guvnor.war 
    to guvnor-webapp.war. Copy the WAR file into the deployment directory of you
    app server, and then start your app server. If you need to customize some
    settings, you can first "explode" (unzip) the war file, and change any
    configuration settings, and then either zip it up, or deploy it
    "exploded". (Note in the JBoss Application Server you will need to make
    sure the exploded folder name ends in ".war")</para>

    <para>Once the guvnor-webapp.war has been placed in the deployment
    directory, and the application server started, you should navigate to
    http://localhost/guvnor-webapp and check that Guvnor appears. (Obviously
    substitute the URL for what your application server is configured
    to).</para>

    <para>Once that shows up, you are deployed and ready to go!</para>

    <section>
      <title>Supported and recommended platforms</title>

      <para>Guvnor is capable of running in any application server that
      supports Java SE5 (JEE 5 is not required) - this includes servlet
      containers like tomcat.</para>

      <para>It is actively tested/developed on JBoss app server platforms,
      which are recommended if you are able to use them, or don't have any
      existing infrastructure. However, it is possible to use any
      container/app server, in some cases with minor configuration tweaks
      (consult the wiki for specific tips - many in the community have been
      able to make it run on various platforms).</para>

      <para>You can download the JBoss app server from www.jboss.com
      for any common operating system.</para>

      <para>Deployment on a JBoss app server: If you are installing a new JBoss
      application server, copy the WAR to [app server
      directory]/server/default/deploy. Start up the server by
      running run.sh or run.bat in the [app server directory]/bin
      directory.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
